{"test_questions": [[{"question": "Diesel used in naval applications has a minimum cetane number of", "opta": "25", "optb": "35", "optc": "45", "optd": "65", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following tests is not done for transformer oil ?", "opta": "Flash point and acid value.", "optb": "Aniline point.", "optc": "Dielectric strength.", "optd": "Copper strip corrosion test.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which is the most undesirable component in kerosene ?", "opta": "Aromatics", "optb": "i-paraffins", "optc": "n-paraffins", "optd": "Naphthenes", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick out the wrong statement about the smoking tendency of various hydrocarbon constituents of kerosene.", "opta": "Smoking tendency of hydrocarbons increases in the order : paraffins \u2192 isoparaffins \u2192 naphthenes \u2192 aromatics.", "optb": "Smoking tendency of paraffins increases with decrease in its molecular weight.", "optc": "Smoking tendency of naphthenes decreases with its increasing molecular weight & also on addition of double bond.", "optd": "Smoking tendency of aromatics decreases with increase in its molecular weight.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Solvent used in duo-sol extraction for lube oil upgradation is a mixture of", "opta": "propane & phenol-cresol mixture.", "optb": "methyl ethyl ketone & glycol.", "optc": "phenol & furfural.", "optd": "propane & liquid sulphur dioxide.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following fractions of a crude oil will have the maximum gravity API (i.e. \u00b0API) ?", "opta": "Diesel", "optb": "Gasoline", "optc": "Atmospheric gas oil", "optd": "Vacuum gas oil", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "For gasoline, the flash point (<50\u00b0C) is determined by the", "opta": "Abel apparatus.", "optb": "Pensky-Marten's apparatus.", "optc": "Saybolt chromometer.", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Flash point of atmospheric distillation residue is determined by __________ apparates.", "opta": "Pensky-Martens (closed cup type).", "optb": "Abel.", "optc": "Cleveland (open cup type)", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Maximum sulphur percentage in low sulphur heavy stock (LSHS) furnace oil is about", "opta": "0.1", "optb": "1", "optc": "2.5", "optd": "3.5", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pour point and freezing point is equal for", "opta": "petrol", "optb": "diesel", "optc": "water", "optd": "crude petroleum", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Smoke point of a test sample of kerosene is found to be 15 mm. On removal of __________ from it, the smoke point rises to 25 mm.", "opta": "n-paraffins", "optb": "olefins", "optc": "aromatics", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "__________ is not an important refinery process for upgrading the quality of lubricating oil.", "opta": "Deoiling", "optb": "Solvent refinning", "optc": "Clay treatment", "optd": "Hydrotreatment", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick out the undesirable property for a solvent meant for dewaxing of lube oil.", "opta": "Complete miscibility with oil.", "optb": "High solubility of wax in the solvent.", "optc": "Both (a) and (b).", "optd": "Neither (a) nor (b).", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following is used as a catalyst in fluidised bed catalytic cracking ?", "opta": "Silica-magnesia", "optb": "Silica-alumina", "optc": "Bentonite clays", "optd": "All (a), (b) and (c)", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Casing head gasoline is the liquid", "opta": "butane.", "optb": "propane.", "optc": "natural gas.", "optd": "gasoline separated from wet natural gas by compression.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Most commonly used crude heater before the fractionation tower in a refinery is the __________ heater.", "opta": "electric immersion", "optb": "pipestill", "optc": "steam coil", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Viscosity index of a lubricating oil", "opta": "is the measure of its flash point.", "optb": "is the measure of variation of viscosity with temperature.", "optc": "should be low.", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Visbreaking process is used mainly for making", "opta": "high cetane diesel", "optb": "high octane gasoline", "optc": "fuel oil", "optd": "smoke free kerosene", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Operating condition in the electrical dehydrators for crude oil is about", "opta": "6.5 kgf/Cm2 & 95\u00b0C.", "optb": "1 atm. & 110 \u00b0C.", "optc": "20 kgf/cm2 & 110\u00b0C.", "optd": "50 atm. and 150\u00b0C.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Crude oil is pumped by a __________ pump.", "opta": "gear", "optb": "centrifugal", "optc": "screw", "optd": "reciprocating", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Solvent used in the deasphalting process is", "opta": "furfurol", "optb": "phenol", "optc": "propane", "optd": "hexane", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A good lubricant should have high", "opta": "viscosity index", "optb": "volatility", "optc": "pour point", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Complete removal of __________ from gasoline is done by Unisol process using caustic soda and methyl alcohol.", "opta": "waxes", "optb": "mercaptans", "optc": "asphalt", "optd": "diolefins", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The main use of heavy gas oil produced by the vacuum distillation unit is as a", "opta": "blending component for kerosene.", "optb": "blending component for petrol.", "optc": "feedstock for fluid catalytic cracking unit.", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Stabilisation of gasoline (petrol) means", "opta": "removal of dissolved gases from it.", "optb": "increasing its oxidation stability.", "optc": "improving its lead susceptibility.", "optd": "increasing its vapour pressure.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In petroleum refining, the process used for conversion of hydrocarbons to aromatics is", "opta": "catalytic cracking", "optb": "catalytic reforming", "optc": "hydrotreating", "optd": "alkylation", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Diesel index.(an alternative index for expressing the quality of diesel) is", "opta": "determined by using a test engine.", "optb": "not related to aniline point.", "optc": "equal to cetane number plus 3.", "optd": "all (a), (b) & (c).", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Octane number of gasoline is a measure of its", "opta": "resistance to knock.", "optb": "ignition delay.", "optc": "ignition temperature.", "optd": "smoke point.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick out the additive property of a lube oil out of following.", "opta": "\u00b0API gravity", "optb": "Specific gravity", "optc": "Viscosity", "optd": "Flashpoint", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Catalyst used in catalytic reforming is", "opta": "platinum on alumina", "optb": "nickel", "optc": "iron", "optd": "aluminium chloride", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Tanks used for the storage of petroleum products (which are inflammable) should be painted with a __________ paint.", "opta": "black", "optb": "white", "optc": "red", "optd": "yellow", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Cetane number of diesel used in trucks may be about", "opta": "50", "optb": "14", "optc": "35", "optd": "85", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Generally, diesel engines operate well with a Cetane number from 40 to 55."}, {"question": "__________ test is done to find out the softening point of bitumen.", "opta": "Impact", "optb": "Ball and ring", "optc": "Flame", "optd": "Viscosity", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "__________ determination is not a very significant and important test for gasoline.", "opta": "Gum & sulphur content", "optb": "Viscosity", "optc": "Octane number", "optd": "Reid vapor pressure", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following has the lowest viscosity (at a given temperature) of all?", "opta": "Naphtha", "optb": "Kerosene", "optc": "Diesel", "optd": "Lube oil", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Mercaptans are", "opta": "low boiling sulphur compounds.", "optb": "added in LPG cylinders to detect gas leakage by its smell.", "optc": "undesirable in petrol, as they reduce its octane number.", "optd": "all (a), (b) and (c)", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Paraffin base crude oil as compared to asphalt base crude gives", "opta": "higher yield of straight run gasoline.", "optb": "higher octane number gasoline.", "optc": "lower viscosity index lube oil.", "optd": "poorer yield of lube oil.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "True boiling point apparatus is used for the", "opta": "determination of characterisation factor.", "optb": "evaluation of oil stocks.", "optc": "determination of true vapour pressure.", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In the atmospheric pressure crude distillation, the content of __________ from lighter fraction to heavier ones.", "opta": "sulphur increases", "optb": "sulphur decreases", "optc": "nitrogen decreases", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Catalytic desulphurisation process used for sweetening of straight run gasoline and kerosene uses __________ as catalyst.", "opta": "bauxite", "optb": "fuller's earth", "optc": "activated clay", "optd": "all (a), (b) & (c)", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Solution used in Doctor's treatment for the removal of mercaptans is", "opta": "sodium hydroxide", "optb": "sodium plumbite", "optc": "cupric chloride", "optd": "potassium isobutyrate", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Flash point of motor gasoline may be around __________ \u00b0C.", "opta": "10", "optb": "45", "optc": "100", "optd": "150", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "__________ converts n-paraffins to i-paraffins.", "opta": "Alkylation", "optb": "Polymerisation", "optc": "Isomerisation", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The colour of gasoline is an indication of its", "opta": "octane number.", "optb": "lead susceptibility.", "optc": "gum forming tendency & thoroughness of refining.", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The octane number of aviation gasoline may be", "opta": "79", "optb": "87", "optc": "97", "optd": ">100", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Flash point of an oil gives an idea of the", "opta": "nature of boiling point diagram of the system.", "optb": "amount of low boiling fraction present.", "optc": "explosion hazards.", "optd": "all (a), (b) and (c).", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Furfural solvent extraction is used for upgrading (by dissolving aromatics)", "opta": "naphtha", "optb": "lubricating oils", "optc": "wax", "optd": "cracking feedstock", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Illuminating characteristics of kerosene is expressed by its", "opta": "smoke point", "optb": "aniline point", "optc": "luminosity number", "optd": "aromatic content", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following constituents present in petroleum is responsible for ash formation?", "opta": "Nitrogen compounds", "optb": "Organometallic compounds", "optc": "Sulphur compounds", "optd": "Oxygen compounds", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The coking process normally mostly used in Indian oil refineries is the __________ coking process.", "opta": "delayed", "optb": "flexi", "optc": "fluid", "optd": "contact", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}]]}